<?xml version="1.0"?>
<book version="5.0" xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook http://www.docbook.org/xml/5.0CR7/xsd/docbook.xsd"
>
  <info>
    <title>S7nodave for EPICS Manual</title>
    <copyright>
      <year>2011</year>
      <year>2012</year>
      <year>2015</year>
      <year>2021</year>
      <holder>aquenos GmbH</holder>
    </copyright>
    <author>
      <personname>
        <firstname>Sebastian</firstname>
        <surname>Marsching</surname>
      </personname>
      <affiliation>
        <orgname>aquenos GmbH</orgname>
      </affiliation>
    </author>
  </info>
  <chapter xml:id="introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>
    <para>
      This manual is divided in six chapters (not counting this introduction).
      The <link linkend="concept">first chapter</link> introduces the concepts 
      and features of the s7nodave device support for EPICS.
      The <link linkend="gettingstarted">second chapter</link> describes the
      few steps needed to start an IOC project making use of s7nodave.
      The <link linkend="iocshreference">third chapter</link> describes the
      IOC shell commands supported by s7nodave.
      Subsequently, the <link linkend="recordreference">fourth chapter</link>
      explains the various record types supported by s7nodave.
      Finally, the <link linkend="pollgroups">fifth chapter</link> explains
      how to use poll groups.
    </para>
    <para>
      If you have used this software before and are upgrading to a newer
      version, you might find the <link linkend="news">appendix</link> useful
      that describes the changes that have been made in recent version and how
      you might need to update your project to match these changes.
      been made compared 
    </para>
    <warning>
      <para>
        When using this software to connect to a PLC, disconnect
        <emphasis>all</emphasis> external equipment from the PLC before trying
        to establish a connection.
      </para>
      <para>
        This software can overwrite variables in the PLC memory or even parts of
        the program running in the PLC. Therefore outputs of the PLC might show 
        unpredictable behavior.
      </para>
      <para>
        There are a lot of different PLC types and depending on the type of the
        PLC, its configuration, the type of the host machine used for the EPICS 
        IOC, the host machine's configuration and the EPICS IOC's configuration,
        this software might have very different, potentially unwanted results.
      </para>
      <para>
        It is always the responsibility of the user using this software to
        ensure, that its use is safe and complies with local regulation
        <emphasis>before</emphasis> connecting any equipment to the PLC.
        Violations of this rules might result in equipment being damaged or even
        <emphasis>persons being injured</emphasis> by misbehaving equipment.
      </para>
    </warning>
  </chapter>
  
  <chapter xml:id="concept">
    <title>Concept</title>
    <para>
      This chapter introduces the concept of the s7nodave device support and
      the features offered by it.
    </para>
    <section>
      <title>Snap7</title>
      <para>
        The s7nodave device support is based on 
        <link xlink:href="http://snap7.sourceforge.net/">Snap7</link>. This
        library implements the communication protocol supported by many PLCs
        from the S7 family and thus allows software on a PC to communicate with
        a PLC without having to explicitly implement communication routines on
        the PLC side.
      </para>
      <para>
        In the past, the s7nodave device support had been based on
        <link xlink:href="http://libnodave.sourceforge.net/">libnodave</link>.
        This changed with the release of s7nodave version 3.0 because of a bug
        in libnodave that could not be easily fixed.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Supported Devices</title>
      <para>
        Basically, s7nodave supports all PLCs supported by
        <link xlink:href="http://snap7.sourceforge.net/">Snap7</link>.
      </para>
      <para>
        S7nodave has been developed using a S7-1200 PLC. However, we have also
        seen it work with S7-300 and S7-1500 PLCs.
      </para>
      <para>
        For new version of PLCs or TIA Portal, (in particular S7-1200 and
        S7-1500 series PLCs and TIA Portal version 12 and newer) the settings
        in the S7 project might have to be changed in order to allow full access
        to the PLCs memory. You might only be able to access global DBs and
        optimized block access for those DBs must be disabled. In addition to
        that, the access level must be set to <guilabel>full</guilabel> and the
        <guilabel>connection mechanism</guilabel> must allow GET/PUT
        communication. Please refer to the
        <link xlink:href="http://snap7.sourceforge.net/snap7_client.html#1200_1500">information available from the Snap7 project</link>
        for a more detailed guide, including screenshots of the relevant
        configuration dialogs.
      </para>
      <important>
        <para>
          It is the responsibility of each user to verify, that the PLC being
          used is compatible with this software. The author of this software
          does not assume any liability regarding the compatibility of this
          software with a certain PLC or the eligibility for a certain
          application.
        </para>
      </important>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Communication between the PLC and EPICS</title>
      <para>
        The
        <link xlink:href="http://epics.web.psi.ch/software/s7plc/">S7plc</link>
        driver from PSI is based on a whole data-block being exchanged between
        the PLC and the EPICS IOC. This means, that it is not possible to write
        single records to the PLC. Instead, all values must be sent at once.
        The same applies to read requests. Besides, the structure of the
        data-block is coded into a PLC program. If a value is added or removed
        from the block, the addresses in the PLC logic as well as in the EPICS
        record configuration have to be updated.
      </para>
      <para>
        The s7nodave device support on the other hand, directly reads from and
        writes to memory addresses in the PLC. The addresses configured in the
        EPICS records use the same notation that is used for programming the PLC
        logic. When an output record is process, on the value of this record
        is sent to the PLC. For input records, different records can be
        processed at different rates and only the values in the same
        <link linkend="pollgroups">poll group</link> are transferred together.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Integration into EPICS</title>
      <para>
        S7nodave is implemented as an asynchronous device support based on
        <link xlink:href="http://www.aps.anl.gov/epics/modules/soft/asyn/">asynDriver</link>.
        While the asynDriver is used for configuration management, logging and
        asynchronous processing, neither the device support nor the low-level
        I/O routines supported by the asynDriver are used.
      </para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  
  <chapter xml:id="gettingstarted">
    <title>Getting Started</title>
    <para>
      This chapter describes the steps needed to setup a simple project using
      s7nodave. First, the prerequisites for using s7nodave are described.
      Subsequently, the installation and compilation of the s7nodave device
      support is explained. Finally, the steps needed to include the s7nodave
      device support in a project are shown.
    </para>
    <section>
      <title>Prerequisites</title>
      <para>
        S7nodave has three prerequisites: First, 
        <link xlink:href="http://www.aps.anl.gov/epics/">EPICS base</link>
        R3.14.12 or higher is  needed. Older versions of EPICS base might work
         but in this case support for the <literal>aai</literal> and
         <literal>aao</literal> record types must be disabled, because these
         record types were broken in earlier versions of EPICS base.
      </para>
      <para>
        In addition to that, the
        <link xlink:href="http://www.aps.anl.gov/epics/modules/soft/asyn/">asynDriver</link>
        is needed. S7nodave has been developed against version 4.13 of asyn,
        however most likely it also works with newer versions.
      </para>
      <para>
        A minimal version of Snap7 that contains all the parts needed by
        s7nodave is bundled with s7nodave and automatically compiled when
        s7nodave is compiled. Thus, you do not need to download or compile Snap7
        yourself.
      </para>
      <para>
        S7nodave has been developed under Linux, but should work on most
        POSIX-compliant operating systems. On Microsoft Windows, you will
        have to use a compatibility layer like Cygwin or change the network
        code in s7nodave to use the respective functions from the Windows API.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Compiling the Prerequisites</title>
      <para>
        For compiling EPICS Base and the asynDriver, refer to the respective
        manuals.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Compiling s7nodave</title>
      <para>
        After downloading s7nodave from the
        <link xlink:href="http://oss.aquenos.com/epics/s7nodave/">project website</link>,
        extract it to the directory you want it to install in. A good place
        might be the <filename>/opt/epics/modules</filename> directory.
      </para>
      <para>
        Subsequently, you have edit add the file
        <filename>configure/RELEASE.local</filename> in order to configure the
        locations where EPICS base and the asynDriver are installed. Add the
        variables <literal>ASYN</literal> and <literal>EPICS_BASE</literal> to
        this file and make them point to the right directories. You can find an
        example in <filename>configure/EXAMPLE_RELEASE.local</filename>.
      </para>
      <para>
        S7nodave must be compiled with a C++ compiler that supports C++ 11. For
        some compilers, C++ 11 support is not enabled by default. In this case,
        you have to add the file
        <filename>configure/CONFIG_SITE.local</filename> and append the
        appropriate compiler options to the <literal>USR_CXXFLAGS</literal>
        variable. An example for such a configuration file can be found in
        <filename>configure/EXAMPLE_CONFIG_SITE.local</filename>.
      </para>
      <para>
        After editing this paths, you can run <command>make</command> to build
        s7nodave.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Using s7nodave in a project</title>
      <para>
        In the <filename>configure/RELEASE</filename> file of your project, you
        have to add a line like
        <literal>S/NODAVE=/opt/epics/modules/s7nodave</literal>. In the
        <filename>Makefile</filename> of the <filename>src</filename> directory
        of you application (e.g. <filename>myApp/src/Makefile</filename>) you
        have to add something like
<programlisting><![CDATA[
my_DBD += s7nodave.dbd
my_LIBS += s7nodave
]]></programlisting>
        in order to use the s7nodave device support in your record definition
        files.
      </para>
      <para>
        Finally, you have to configure at least one PLC connection in the
        startup file of your IOC. See
        <xref linkend="iocsh.s7nodaveConfigureIsoTcpPort" /> for the syntax of
        the corresponding command. Optionally, you also might want to configure
        <link linkend="iocsh.s7nodaveConfigurePollGroup">poll groups</link>. For
        defining records that read from or write to the PLC, please refer to the
        <link linkend="recordreference">record reference</link>.
      </para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  
  <chapter xml:id="iocshreference">
    <title>IOC Shell Reference</title>
    <para>
      S7nodave supports IOC shell commands for configuring a PLC connection and
      for adding <link linkend="pollgroups">poll groups</link>. In addition to
      that, the
      <link xlink:href="http://www.aps.anl.gov/epics/modules/soft/asyn/R4-16/asynDriver.html#DiagnosticAids">asyn commands</link>
      for configuring the trace mask and trace I/O mask are supported. However,
      you have to add <filename>asyn.dbd</filename> to the list of DBDs used
      by your project in order to enable these commands in the IOC shell.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="iocsh.s7nodaveConfigureIsoTcpPort">
      <title>s7nodaveConfigureIsoTcpPort</title>
      <para>
        The <literal>s7nodaveConfigureIsoTcpPort</literal> command is used to
        setup a connection to a PLC and command has the
        following syntax:
      </para>
      <para>
        <synopsis>s7nodaveConfigureIsoTcpPort(PLC name, PLC hostname or IP address, PLC rack number, PLC slot number, thread priority)</synopsis>
        The <literal>PLC name</literal> is an arbitrary string, that is used to
        refer to this PLC in the device address field of 
        <link linkend="recordreference">records</link> and when
        <link linkend="iocsh.s7nodaveConfigurePollGroup">configuring poll groups</link>
        for the PLC. However, the PLC name may not contain whitespace or
        parentheses.
      </para>
      <para>
        The <literal>PLC hostname or IP address</literal> is the DNS hostname or
        IP address of the PLC, optionally followed by the TCP port number
        (separated from the hostname or IP address by a colon). If no port
        number is specified, the default port (102) is used.
      </para>
      <para>
        The <literal>PLC rack number</literal> and
        <literal>PLC slot number</literal> depend on the actual PLC
        configuration. For most setups, both numbers are zero, but rack 0,
        slot 2 might have to be used with some S7-300 series PLCs. If you cannot
        get access to the PLC, try to change those numbers. In case of doubt,
        you should be able to find the correct numbers in the configuration of
        your S7 project. You can find more information about rack and slot
        numbers in the reference manual of the
        <link xlink:href="http://snap7.sourceforge.net/">Snap7 library</link>.
      </para>
      <para>
        The <literal>thread priority</literal> is the priority used for the
        communication thread (port thread in asyn nomenclature). If a priority
        of <literal>0</literal> is specified, the priority
        <literal>epicsThreadPriorityMedium</literal> is used.
      </para>
      <para>
        An example line configuring a connection to a PLC might look like this:
      </para>
      <para>
        <literal>s7nodaveConfigureIsoTcpPort("myPLC", "myplc.example.com", 0, 0, 0)</literal>
      </para>
      <para>
        You can have multiple instances of
        <literal>s7nodaveConfigureIsoTcpPort</literal> in your IOC startup
        configuration, however the PLC name used must be unique for each
        instance.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="iocsh.s7nodaveConfigurePollGroup">
      <title>s7nodaveConfigurePollGroup</title>
      <para>
        The <literal>s7nodaveConfigurePollGroup</literal> command is used for
        configuring <link linkend="pollgroups">poll groups</link> and has the
        following syntax:
      </para>
      <para>
        <synopsis>s7nodaveConfigurePollGroup(PLC name, poll-group name, poll interval, thread priority)</synopsis>
        The <literal>PLC name</literal> must be the name of a PLC previously
        used in an instance of
        <link linkend="iocsh.s7nodaveConfigureIsoTcpPort"><literal>s7nodaveConfigureIsoTcpPort</literal></link>.
      </para>
      <para>
        The <literal>poll-group name</literal> is an arbitrary string that
        identifies the poll-group and must be unique for the PLC. However, the
        same poll-group name may be used for two different PLCs. The poll-group
        name must no contain whitespace, parentheses, the equal sign or commas.
      </para>
      <para>
        The <literal>poll interval</literal> is a floating point number that
        specifies the interval in which the memory addresses belonging to the
        poll group are read. The units of the poll interval are seconds.
      </para>
      <para>
        The <literal>thread priority</literal> specifies the priority of the
        thread, that periodically processes the poll group. If a priority of
        <literal>0</literal> is specified, the priority
        <literal>epicsThreadPriorityMedium</literal> is used.
      </para>
      <para>
        An example line configuring a poll group that is processed once a second
        might look like this:
      </para>
      <para>
        <literal>s7nodaveConfigurePollGroup("myPLC", "1s", 1.0, 0)</literal>
      </para>
      <para>
        You can have multiple instances of
        <literal>s7nodaveConfigurePollGroup</literal> per PLC, however the
        poll-group name used must be unique for each instance referring to the
        same PLC.
      </para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  
  <chapter xml:id="recordreference">
    <title>Record Reference</title>
    <para>
      In this chapter, first the format of the device addresses used for the
      s7nodave device support is explained. Subsequently the various PLC
      data-types supported by s7nodave are described. Finally, details about
      the records, supported by s7nodave, are given.
    </para>
    <section xml:id="recordreference.deviceaddress">
      <title>Device Address Format</title>
      <para>
        In order to use the s7nodave device address support for a record, the
        record's device type field (<literal>DTYP</literal>) has to specify
        <literal>s7nodave</literal>. This device type is used for all records
        supported by s7nodave except the
        <link linkend="record.waveform">waveform</link> record.
      </para>
      <para>
        The record's device address field (usually <literal>INP</literal> for
        input and <literal>OUT</literal> for output records) must specify a
        device address recognized by the s7nodave.
      </para>
      <para>
        In general, a device address for s7nodave has the following format:
      </para>
      <para>
        <synopsis>@PLC-name[(param1=value1,param2=value2,...)] PLC-address [PLC-data-type]</synopsis>
        The exact supported options may vary depending on the record type.
      </para>
      <para>
        Every device address start with the <literal>@</literal>-sign, followed
        by the PLC name. The PLC name must be the name of a PLC configured using
        the
        <link linkend="iocsh.s7nodaveConfigureIsoTcpPort">s7nodaveConfigureIsoTcpPort</link>
        statement in the IOC startup file.
      </para>
      <para>
        The PLC name is followed by list of optional parameters wrapped in
        parentheses. If no parameters are given, the parentheses can be
        ommitted. The supported parameters depend on the record type.
        Please see <xref linkend="recordreference.parameters" /> and
        <xref linkend="recordreference.records" /> for details. If multiple
        parameters are specified, they are separated by commas.
      </para>
      <para>
        The PLC memory address is separated from the PLC name (or the optional
        parameter list) by whitespace. 
        Please refer to <xref linkend="recordreference.plcaddress" />
        for the the format of the PLC memory address.
      </para>
      <para>
        Finally, an optional PLC data-type, which is separated from the PLC
        memory address by whitespace, can be specified. If no PLC data-type is
        specified, the data-type is guessed based on the record-type and PLC
        memory address. Please refer to
        <xref linkend="recordreference.plctypes" /> and
        <xref linkend="recordreference.parameters" /> for details about the
        supported PLC data-types.
      </para>
      <para>
        Examples for valid device addresses:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>@myPLC(DLV=0,DHV=27648) IW64</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>@myPLC(DLV=0,DHV=27648) IW66 int16</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>@myPLC IB0</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>@myPLC QB0</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="recordreference.plcaddress">
      <title>PLC Memory Addresses</title>
      <para>
        S7nodave uses the same format for PLC memory addresses, that is also
        usually used for programming the PLCs (e.g. using Step7 or WinPLC).
        The English and the German notation are both supported and equivalent
        to each other.
      </para>
      <para>
        This format combines the specification of the start-byte of a variable
        in the PLC memory with specification of the variable's width.
      </para>
      <para>
        The PLC address starts with the memory area. The following memory areas
        are supported:
      </para>
      <table>
        <title>PLC Memory Areas</title>
        <tgroup cols="3" align="left">
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>English</entry>
              <entry>German</entry>
              <entry>Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>DBn.DB</entry>
              <entry>DBn.DB</entry>
              <entry>Data Blocks (n must be an integer number)</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>F</entry>
              <entry>M</entry>
              <entry>Flags</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>I</entry>
              <entry>E</entry>
              <entry>Input Memory Image</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>Q</entry>
              <entry>A</entry>
              <entry>Output Memory Image</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>T</entry>
              <entry>T</entry>
              <entry>Timers</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>C</entry>
              <entry>Z</entry>
              <entry>Counters</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para>
        For data block addresses the data-block number has to be included in the
        area specification. For addresses using the data-block, flags,
        input-memory and output memory areas, you next have to specify the width
        of the memory that should be read from or written to. The notation used
        for specifying the width is:
      </para>
      <table>
        <title>PLC Memory Width</title>
        <tgroup cols="2" align="left">
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Notation</entry>
              <entry>Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>X</entry>
              <entry>Bit (only for DB areas, other areas use the empty string instead)</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>B</entry>
              <entry>Byte (8 bits)</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>W</entry>
              <entry>Word (16 bits)</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>D</entry>
              <entry>Double Word (32 bits)</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para>
        For addresses referring to a single bit (with the exception of bit 
        addresses in DB areas) and for addresses referring to
        the counter or timer areas, no width specification is given: Bit
        addresses are identified by specifying the bit within the byte and the
        counter and timer areas always use word (16-bit) values.
      </para>
      <para>
        After specifying the memory width, the start address must be specified.
        The start address is always given in the number of bytes counted from
        the beginning of the respective area (starting with zero). For example,
        if at the beginning of <literal>DB1</literal> two 32-bit numbers were
        stored, the two addresses for these numbers would be
        <literal>DB1.DBD0</literal> and <literal>DB1.DBD4</literal>.
      </para>
      <para>
        For addresses referring to a single bit, the start bit within the byte
        has to be specified, separated from the start byte by a dot. For
        example, in order to refer to the first bit of the first byte in the
        input-memory area, you would use the address <literal>I0.0</literal>.
        You must not specify a start bit for byte, word or double-word
        addresses.
      </para>
      <para>
        PLC memory-address specifications are not case-sensitive. However, for
        enhanced readability the use of upper case characters is recommended.
      </para>
      <para>
        Examples for valid memory addresses:
      </para>
      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para>DB3.DBD4</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>FW4</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>IB2</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Q8.3</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>DB50.DBX17.3</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>T2</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>C2</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="recordreference.plctypes">
      <title>PLC Data-Types</title>
      <para>
        s7nodave supports eight different PLC data-types. Each of these
        data-types may only be used together with a memory address having the
        right width:
      </para>
      <table>
        <title>PLC Data Types and their Corresponding Memory Width</title>
        <tgroup cols="3" align="left">
          <thead>
            <row>
              <entry>Data Type</entry>
              <entry>Memory Width</entry>
              <entry>Description</entry>
            </row>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <row>
              <entry>bool</entry>
              <entry>1 bit</entry>
              <entry>Boolean</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>int8</entry>
              <entry>Byte (8 bits)</entry>
              <entry>Signed Integer</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>uint8</entry>
              <entry>Byte (8 bits)</entry>
              <entry>Unsigned Integer</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>int16</entry>
              <entry>Word (16 bits)</entry>
              <entry>Signed Integer</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>uint16</entry>
              <entry>Word (16 bits)</entry>
              <entry>Unsigned Integer</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>int32</entry>
              <entry>Double Word (32 bits)</entry>
              <entry>Signed Integer</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>uint32</entry>
              <entry>Double Word (32 bits)</entry>
              <entry>Unsigned Integer</entry>
            </row>
            <row>
              <entry>float</entry>
              <entry>Double Word (32 bits)</entry>
              <entry>Single Precision Floating Point Number</entry>
            </row>
          </tbody>
        </tgroup>
      </table>
      <para>
        The available data-types are also limited by the used record-type.
        Please refer to <xref linkend="recordreference.records"/> for details.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="recordreference.parameters">
      <title>Supported Parameters</title>
      <para>
        There is a number of optional parameters that can be used to specify
        device-support specific options for a record. Most of these options
        are only valid for a specific record-type, so please refer to the
        description of the respective options for finding out which option can
        be used with which record type.
      </para>
      <section xml:id="recordreference.parameters.pg">
        <title>PG - Specifying a Poll Group</title>
        <para>
          The <literal>PG</literal> parameter can be used with all input
          records to specify a <link linkend="pollgroups">poll group</link> 
          for the record. It is only valid, if the <literal>SCAN</literal> field
          of the record is set to <literal>I/O Intr</literal>.
          Example: <literal>@myPLC(PG=1s) IW64</literal>
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="recordreference.parameters.dlvdhv">
        <title>DLV, DHV - Specifying Device Value Limits</title>
        <para>
          The <literal>DLV</literal> and <literal>DHV</literal> parameters
          specify the lower and upper bounds of the raw values read from or
          written to the PLC. These values together with the record fields
          <literal>EGUL</literal> and <literal>EGUF</literal> are used for
          converting raw values to values in engineering units and vice-versa,
          when the record's <literal>LINR</literal> field is set to
          <literal>LINEAR</literal>.
        </para>
        <para>
          If linear conversion is enabled, the conversion parameters are set
          in such a way, that a raw value of <literal>DLV</literal> corresponds
          to an engineering units value of <literal>EGUL</literal> and a raw
          value of <literal>DHV</literal> corresponds to an engineering units
          value of <literal>EGUF</literal>.
          Please refer to the description of the
          <literal>ai</literal> and <literal>ao</literal> records in the
          <link xlink:href="http://www.aps.anl.gov/epics/wiki/index.php/RRM_3-14">EPICS Record Reference Manual</link>
          for details about linear conversion.
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="recordreference.records">
      <title>Supported Records</title>
      <para>
        S7nodave supports most records from EPICS base, that have an interface
        for device support routines. In order to use s7nodave with a record,
        the record's <literal>DTYP</literal> and <literal>INP</literal> or
        <literal>OUT</literal> fields have to be set correctly. Please refer to
        <xref linkend="recordreference.deviceaddress" /> for details. This
        chapter describe the specific options for each supported record type.
      </para>
      <para>
        This manual only describe those features of each record, which are
        specific to the s7nodave device support. Please refer to the
        <link xlink:href="http://www.aps.anl.gov/epics/wiki/index.php/RRM_3-14">EPICS Record Reference Manual</link>
        for a general description of each record type and its fields.
      </para>
      <section xml:id="record.aai">
        <title>aai - Array Input</title>
        <para>
          The <literal>aai</literal> record is used for reading multiple
          elements from the PLC's memory into an array. The supported
          PLC data-types depend on the EPICS data-type specified in the
          record's <literal>FTVL</literal> field, as described in this
          table:
        </para>
        <table rowheader="firstcol">
          <title>Mapping of PLC Types to EPICS Types</title>
          <tgroup cols="9" align="center">
            <colspec colname="start" colnum="1" align="left"/>
            <colspec colname="end" colnum="9"/>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry>bool</entry>
                <entry>int8</entry>
                <entry>uint8</entry>
                <entry>int16</entry>
                <entry>uint16</entry>
                <entry>int32</entry>
                <entry>uint32</entry>
                <entry>float</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tfoot>
              <row>
                <entry namest="start" nameend="end">
                  X = default for memory addresses of the corresponding width,
                  o = supported, if specified explicitly
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tfoot>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>STRING</entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry>o</entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>CHAR</entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>UCHAR</entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>SHORT</entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry>o</entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>USHORT</entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>LONG</entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry>o</entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry>o</entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>ULONG</entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>FLOAT</entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry>o</entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry>o</entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry>o</entry>
                <entry>o</entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>DOUBLE</entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry>o</entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry>o</entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry>o</entry>
                <entry>o</entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>ENUM</entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
        <para>
          For all EPICS data-types except <literal>STRING</literal>, the width
          of the PLC data-type has to match the width of the PLC address. In
          this case, the total number of bytes read is the width of the PLC
          data-type multiplied by the number of elements in the array. The PLC
          memory address specified is the start of the first element in the
          array.
        </para>
        <para>
          If <literal>FTVL</literal> is set to <literal>STRING</literal>, the
          PLC memory-address must be a byte. This byte is regarded to be the
          first byte of the first string in the array. In total, fourty bytes
          are read for each element in the array. For example, if the array has
          ten elements, 400 bytes are read from the PLC memory.
        </para>
        <para>
          If the PLC address specified refers to a bit, the number of bits read
          from the PLC equals the number of elements in the array. The read does
          not have to be aligned to byte boundaries.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="record.aao">
        <title>aao - Array Output</title>
        <para>
          The <literal>aao</literal> record is used for writing multiple
          elements from an array into the PLC's memory. The supported
          PLC data-types depend on the EPICS data-type specified in the
          record's <literal>FTVL</literal> field, as described in this
          table:
        </para>
        <table rowheader="firstcol">
          <title>Mapping of EPICS Types to PLC Types</title>
          <tgroup cols="9" align="center">
            <colspec colname="start" colnum="1" align="left"/>
            <colspec colname="end" colnum="9"/>
            <thead>
              <row>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry>bool</entry>
                <entry>int8</entry>
                <entry>uint8</entry>
                <entry>int16</entry>
                <entry>uint16</entry>
                <entry>int32</entry>
                <entry>uint32</entry>
                <entry>float</entry>
              </row>
            </thead>
            <tfoot>
              <row>
                <entry namest="start" nameend="end">
                  X = default for memory addresses of the corresponding width,
                  o = supported, if specified explicitly
                </entry>
              </row>
            </tfoot>
            <tbody>
              <row>
                <entry>STRING</entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry>o</entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>CHAR</entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry>o</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>UCHAR</entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry>o</entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry>o</entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry>o</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>SHORT</entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry>o</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>USHORT</entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry>o</entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry>o</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>LONG</entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry>o</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>ULONG</entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry>o</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>FLOAT</entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry>o</entry>
                <entry>o</entry>
                <entry>o</entry>
                <entry>o</entry>
                <entry>o</entry>
                <entry>o</entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>DOUBLE</entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry>o</entry>
                <entry>o</entry>
                <entry>o</entry>
                <entry>o</entry>
                <entry>o</entry>
                <entry>o</entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
              </row>
              <row>
                <entry>ENUM</entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry></entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry>o</entry>
                <entry>X</entry>
                <entry>o</entry>
              </row>
            </tbody>
          </tgroup>
        </table>
        <para>
          For all EPICS data-types except <literal>STRING</literal>, the width
          of the PLC data-type has to match the width of the PLC address. In
          this case, the total number of bytes written is the width of the PLC
          data-type multiplied by the number of elements in the array. The PLC
          memory address specified is the start of the first element in the
          array.
        </para>
        <para>
          If <literal>FTVL</literal> is set to <literal>STRING</literal>, the
          PLC memory-address must be a byte. This byte is regarded to be the
          first byte of the first string in the array. In total, fourty bytes
          are written for each element in the array. For example, if the array
          has ten elements, 400 bytes are written to the PLC memory.
        </para>
        <para>
          If the PLC address specified refers to a bit, the number of bits
          written to the PLC equals the number of elements in the array.
          The write does not have to be aligned to byte boundaries. Every
          non-zero number is converted to one before being written to the
          corresponding bit.
        </para>
        <para>
          Writing a <literal>DOUBLE</literal> value may be connected with loss
          of precision, as the PLC driver only supports single precision
          floating point numbers.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>ai - Analog Input</title>
        <para>
          The <literal>ai</literal> record is used for reading analog values
          from the PLC. For conversion from PLC raw values to engineering units,
          the <literal>DLV</literal> and <literal>DVH</literal> options can be
          used (see <xref linkend="recordreference.parameters.dlvdhv" />).
        </para>
        <para>
          The PLC data-types supported by this record are
          <literal>bool</literal>, <literal>int8</literal>,
          <literal>uint8</literal>, <literal>int16</literal>,
          <literal>uint16</literal>, <literal>int32</literal> and
          <literal>float</literal>. When using the <literal>float</literal>
          type, conversion from raw to engineering units is not supported.
          The value from the PLC memory is directly written to the record's
          <literal>VAL</literal> field instead.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>ao - Analog Output</title>
        <para>
          The <literal>ao</literal> record is used for writing analog values to
          the PLC. For conversion from engineering units to PLC raw units, the
          <literal>DLV</literal> and <literal>DHV</literal> options can be used
          (see <xref linkend="recordreference.parameters.dlvdhv" />).
        </para>
        <para>
          The PLC data-types supported by this record are
          <literal>bool</literal>, <literal>int8</literal>,
          <literal>uint8</literal>, <literal>int16</literal>,
          <literal>uint16</literal>, <literal>int32</literal> and
          <literal>float</literal>. When using the <literal>float</literal>
          type, conversion from engineering to raw units is not supported.
          The value of the record's <literal>VAL</literal> field is written to
          the PLC's memory instead. Please note that the conversion from
          engineering to raw units might be lossy, if the calculated raw value
          does not fit within the specificed PLC data-type.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>bi - Binary Input</title>
        <para>
          The <literal>bi</literal> record is used for reading a binary state
          from the PLC. The PLC data-types supported by this record are
          <literal>bool</literal>, <literal>int8</literal>,
          <literal>uint8</literal>, <literal>int16</literal>,
          <literal>uint16</literal>, <literal>int32</literal>,
          <literal>uint32</literal> and <literal>float</literal>.
        </para>
        <para>
          For all types except <literal>float</literal>, a value that does not
          equal zero is considered to be one. For <literal>float</literal>s,
          a value of <literal>NaN</literal> or <literal>+inf</literal> and
          <literal>-inf</literal> is also considered to be zero.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="record.bo">
        <title>bo - Binary Output</title>
        <para>
          The <literal>bo</literal> record is used to set a binary state in the
          PLC. The PLC data-types supported by this record are
          <literal>bool</literal>, <literal>int8</literal>,
          <literal>uint8</literal>, <literal>int16</literal>,
          <literal>uint16</literal>, <literal>int32</literal>,
          <literal>uint32</literal> and <literal>float</literal>.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>longin - Long Input</title>
        <para>
          The <literal>longin</literal> record is used for reading an integer
          number from the PLC. The PLC data-types supported by this record are
          <literal>bool</literal>, <literal>int8</literal>,
          <literal>uint8</literal>, <literal>int16</literal>,
          <literal>uint16</literal> and <literal>int32</literal>.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>longout - Long Output</title>
        <para>
          The <literal>longout</literal> record is used for writing an integer
          number to the PLC. The PLC data-types supported by this record are
          <literal>bool</literal>, <literal>int8</literal>,
          <literal>uint8</literal>, <literal>int16</literal>,
          <literal>uint16</literal> and <literal>int32</literal>.
        </para>
        <para>
          Please note that the write operation might be lossy, if the value
          written does not fit within the specificed PLC data-type.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>mbbi, mbbiDirect - Multi-Bit Binary Input</title>
        <para>
          The <literal>mbbi</literal> and <literal>mbbiDirect</literal> record
          types are used for reading a state consisting of multiple bits from
          the PLC. The PLC data-types supported by this record are
          <literal>int8</literal>, <literal>uint8</literal>,
          <literal>int16</literal>, <literal>uint16</literal>,
          <literal>int32</literal> and <literal>uint32</literal>.
        </para>
        <para>
          The <literal>SHFT</literal> and <literal>NOBT</literal> fields of the
          record are supported by the s7nodave device support, so that bits
          which are not aligned to the byte boundaries can be read.
        </para>
        <para>
          As far as the s7nodave device support is concerned, there is no
          difference between the <literal>mbbi</literal> and
          <literal>mbbiDirect</literal> record-types. Please refer to the
          <link xlink:href="http://www.aps.anl.gov/epics/wiki/index.php/RRM_3-14">EPICS Record Reference Manual</link>
          for the differences between the two record types.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>mbbo, mbboDirect - Multi-Bit Binary Output</title>
        <para>
          The <literal>mbbo</literal> and <literal>mbboDirect</literal>
          record types are used for writing a state consisting of multiple bits
          to the PLC. The PLC data-types supported by this record are
          <literal>int8</literal>, <literal>uint8</literal>,
          <literal>int16</literal>, <literal>uint16</literal>,
          <literal>int32</literal> and <literal>uint32</literal>.
        </para>
        <para>
          The <literal>SHFT</literal> and <literal>NOBT</literal> fields of the
          record are supported by the s7nodave device support, so that bits
          which are not aligned to the byte boundaries can be written. However,
          the write operation is always applied to the complete byte, setting
          the other bits to zero. If you want to set specific bits without
          touching the other bits in the same byte, you should use the
          <link linkend="record.bo">bo</link> or the
          <link linkend="record.aao">aao</link> record.
        </para>
        <para>
          As far as the s7nodave device support is concerned, there is no
          difference between the <literal>mbbo</literal> and
          <literal>mbboDirect</literal> record-types. Please refert to the
          <link xlink:href="http://www.aps.anl.gov/epics/wiki/index.php/RRM_3-14">EPICS Record Reference Manual</link>
          for the differences between the two record types.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>stringin - String Input</title>
        <para>
          The <literal>stringin</literal> record is used for reading a string
          from the PLC. The PLC data-types supported by this record are
          <literal>bool</literal>, <literal>int8</literal> and
          <literal>uint8</literal>.
        </para>
        <para>
          If either the <literal>int8</literal> (the default) or
          <literal>uint8</literal> data-type is specified, fourty bytes are
          read from the PLC and interpreted as a string.
        </para>
        <para>
          If the <literal>bool</literal> data-type is specified, a single bit
          is read from the PLC and the string is set to TRUE if the bit is one
          and to FALSE if the bit is zero.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section>
        <title>stringout - String Output</title>
        <para>
          The <literal>stringout</literal> record is used for writing a string
          to the PLC. The PLC data-types supported by this record are
          <literal>bool</literal>, <literal>int8</literal> and
          <literal>uint8</literal>.
        </para>
        <para>
          If either the <literal>int8</literal> (the default) or
          <literal>uint8</literal> data-type is specified, the fourty bytes of
          the string stored in the record's <literal>VAL</literal> field are
          written to the PLC.
        </para>
        <para>
          If the <literal>bool</literal> data-type is specified, a single bit
          is written to the PLC. If the string is TRUE or 1, one is written,
          otherwise zero is written.
        </para>
      </section>
      <section xml:id="record.waveform">
        <title>waveform - Array Input or Output</title>
        <para>
          The <literal>waveform</literal> record is an alternative to the
          <link linkend="record.aai">aai</link> and
          <link linkend="record.aao">aao</link> records.
          Unlike the other records, it can act as either an input or an output
          record. The device address is always stored in the record's
          <literal>INP</literal> field. If you want to use the record as an
          input record, you have to set the record's <literal>DTYP</literal>
          field to <literal>s7nodaveWfIn</literal>, if you want to use the
          record as an output record, the field has to be set to
          <literal>s7nodaveWfOut</literal>. Apart from that, as far as the
          s7nodave device support is concerned, this record acts exactly like
          the <literal>aai</literal> or <literal>aao</literal> records.
        </para>
      </section>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  
  <chapter xml:id="pollgroups">
    <title>Poll Groups</title>
    <para>
      If you periodically scan multiple input records, that read data from the
      PLC, this is very inefficient, because each read operation sends a read
      request over the network and has to wait for a response from the PLC.
    </para>
    <para>
      Thus, if multiple input records shall be processed at the same rate, you
      should put the in the same poll-group. The read request for all records
      being in the same poll group are placed in the same read request (unless
      the packet size is exceeded) and sent to the PLC together. Accordingly,
      the response from the PLC to all the read requests is also sent in a
      single packet, thus reducing the number of round-trips needed
      significantly.
    </para>
    <para>
      Poll groups are only supported for input records, because output records
      typically are only processed on change anyway. 
    </para>
    <section>
      <title>Creating a Poll Group</title>
      <para>
        A poll group is created using the
        <link linkend="iocsh.s7nodaveConfigurePollGroup">s7nodaveConfigurePollGroup</link>
        command in the IOC's statup configuration. If you use the poll-group
        name default, this has a special meaning. This poll-group is used for
        all records, that are configured to use a poll group but do not
        explicitly specify the name of the poll group to use. For each PLC that
        is configured, the default poll-group must be configured separately.
      </para>
    </section>
    <section>
      <title>Including a Record in a Poll Group</title>
      <para>
        In order to make a record be processed in a poll group, the
        <literal>SCAN</literal> field of the record has to be set to
        <literal>I/O Intr</literal>. If you want to use a different poll group
        than the default poll-group, you can use the <literal>PG</literal>
        parameter to specify the poll group to use (see 
        <xref linkend="recordreference.parameters.pg" />).
      </para>
    </section>
  </chapter>
  
  <appendix xml:id="news">
    <title>News</title>
    <section xml:id="news.v3.0">
      <title>What's new in s7nodave 3.0</title>
      <para>
        Version 3.0.0 switched the backend library for communication with the
        PLC from
        <link xlink:href="http://libnodave.sourceforge.net/">libnodave</link> to
        <link xlink:href="http://snap7.sourceforge.net/">Snap7</link>.
        For most applications that use the EPICS device support, this change
        should be completely transparent. Only when you wrote C/C++ code directly
        using functions from libnodave, you will have to port this code to
        Snap7.
      </para>
      <para>
        The second major change in version 3.0.0 is that s7nodave now uses
        features from C++ 11, so you will need a compiler that supports at least
        that version of C++. Depending on your compiler, you might have to
        explicitly enable support for C++ 11 (some compilers still expect C++ 03
        by default). Switching to C++ 11 allowed us to get rid of the dependency
        on the Boost library, which makes compiling this device support easier.
      </para>
    </section>
  </appendix>
  
</book>
